<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A true account of the captivity of Thomas Phelps at Machaness in Barbary and of his strange escape in company of Edmund Baxter and others, as also of the burning two of the greatest pirat-ships belonging to that kingdom in the River of Mamora upon the thirteenth day of June 1685 / by Thomas Phelps.</title>
            <author>Phelps, Thomas.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1685</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 59 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 17 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A54661</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing P1982</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R25583</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">09025145</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 09025145</idno>
            <idno type="VID">42259</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A54661)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 42259)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1292:5)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A true account of the captivity of Thomas Phelps at Machaness in Barbary and of his strange escape in company of Edmund Baxter and others, as also of the burning two of the greatest pirat-ships belonging to that kingdom in the River of Mamora upon the thirteenth day of June 1685 / by Thomas Phelps.</title>
                  <author>Phelps, Thomas.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[3], 27 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by H. Hills jun. for Joseph Hindmarsh,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1685.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Voyages and travels.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-12</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-12</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:42259:1"/>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:42259:1" rendition="simple:additions"/> A True ACCOUNT OF THE CAPTIVITY OF Thomas Phelps, AT MACHANESS IN BARBARY, AND Of his ſtrange Eſcape in Company of
<hi>Edmund Baxter</hi> and others, as alſo of the Burning Two of the greateſt <hi>Pirat-Ships</hi> belonging to that Kingdom, in the River of
<hi>Mamora;</hi> upon the Thirteenth day of <hi>June</hi> 1685.</p>
            <p>By <hi>THOMAS PHELPS.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <hi>Hoec olim meminiſſe juvabit.</hi>
            </q>
            <p>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <div type="license_to_print">
                        <p>
                           <hi>Licenced,</hi>
                        </p>
                        <closer>
                           <date>Auguſt the <hi>21ſt.</hi>
                           </date>
                           <signed>R. L'<hi>s.</hi>
                           </signed>
                        </closer>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>H. Hills,</hi> Jun. for
<hi>Joſeph Hindmarſh,</hi> at the <hi>Golden-Ball</hi> over againſt the
<hi>Royal-Exchange</hi> in <hi>Cornhill.</hi> 1685.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:42259:2"/>
            <head>To the Honourable <hi>SAMUEL PEPYS,</hi>
               <abbr>Eſq</abbr>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>HAving by your generous Favour had the Honour of being introduc'd into His Majeſties preſence, where I delivered the ſubſtance of this following Narrative, and being preſs'd by the importunity of Friends to Publiſh it to the World, to which mine own incli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nations were not averſe, as which might tend to the infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation of my fellow Sea-men; as well as ſatisfying the curio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity of my Country-men, who delight in Novel and ſtrange Stories; I thought I ſhould be very far wanting to my ſelf, if I ſhould not implore the Patronage of your ever Honoured Name, for none ever will dare to diſpute the truth of any mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of Fact here delivered, when they ſhall underſtand that it has ſtood the teſt of your ſagacity. Sir, Your Eminent and Steady Loyalty, whereby you aſſerted His Majeſties juſt Rights, and the true Priviledges of your Country in the worſt of times, gives me confidence to expect, that you will vouch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſafe this condeſcenſion to a poor, yet honeſt Sea-man, who have devoted my Life to the Service of His Sacred Majeſty and my Country; who have been a Slave, but now have at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained my freedom, which I prize ſo much the more, in that I can with Heart and Hand ſubſcribe my ſelf,</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>Honourable Sir,</salute>
               <signed>Your moſt Obliged and Humble Servant.Tho. Phelps,</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:42259:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>THE PREFACE TO THE READER.</head>
            <p>SInce my Eſcape from Captivity, and worſe than
<hi>Egyptian</hi> Bondage, I have methinks, enjoy'd a happineſs with which my former life was never acquainted; now that after a Storm and terrible Tempeſt, I have by Miracle put into a ſafe and quiet Harbour, after a moſt miſerable Slavery, to the moſt unreaſonable and Barbarous of Men; now that I enjoy the immunities and freedom of my Native Country, and the Privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledges of a Subject of <hi>England,</hi> altho' my circumſtances other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe are but indifferent, yet I find I am affected with extraor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary emotions and ſingular tranſports of joy; now I know what Liberty is, and can put a value and make a juſt eſtimate of that happineſs, which before I never well underſtood, which ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation agrees very well with a leſſon in Morals I remember I have been taught, <hi>viz.</hi> that all Happineſs here below is only Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lative, and has a value only put upon it by Compariſon, Riches and Abundance have their Meaſures of good and convenience, from the conſideration of the Miſeries and Inconveniencies that attend Poverty and Want; Health can be but ſlightly eſteemed by him, who never was acquáinted with Pain or Sickneſs, and Liberty and Freedom are the happineſs only valuable by a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flection on Captivity and Slavery, they who are unacquainted <pb facs="tcp:42259:3"/> with, and have no notice of the Miſeries of the latter, will ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver put a due Value and conſideration upon the former; of which general Rule, the moſt part of my Country-men, I am ſorry to ſay, are too particular an inſtance, who of all the Nations of the Earth are poſſeſſors of the greateſt Liberty, but leaſt ſenſible of the happineſs; Here the Government ſecures every Man in the poſſeſſion and enjoyment of what Gods bleſſing and his own induſtry has allow'd; Here even the Poor and Needy, the Impotent, and thoſe whom the Hand of God has touch'd, have a comfortable ſubſiſtence, and plentiful proviſion againſt all extremities; Here the induſtrious Mechanick or Country-Farmer, can ſit down at his Table better provided than many Barons of <hi>Germany,</hi> Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſes in <hi>France,</hi> and Knights in <hi>Spain;</hi> in a word Slavery is ſo ſtrange a condition to
<hi>England,</hi> that to touch its ſoil, is <hi>ipſo facto Manumiſſion,</hi> and the generality of the People have but little heard, and leſs underſtood the miſerable State which the moſt part of the World is now ſubject to, ſo that the Plenty and great Liberty of the
<hi>Engliſh</hi> Subjects is no great happineſs to them, becauſe they never weigh their Condition with what is the Lot of other Nations: Upon this conſideration I have adven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tured to Publiſh this account of the Miſeries I underwent, with many others, during our Captivity in <hi>Barbary,</hi> and of my Eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cape thence. My deſign is, Chriſtian Reader, to work in thee by this true, tho' plain Narrative, ſome pitty towards the ſharp ſufferings of thy poor Brethren at the hands of Infidels; to inſtruct thee to prize the bleſſings of that pleaſant place, where thy Let is fallen, and where having only the benefit of Air, thou haſt a goodly Heritage; and laſtly with me, to Magnifie the Name of God, who in his word, commands us to tell what things he hath done for us, and to ſhew forth his works with gladneſs.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div n="captivity" type="account">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:42259:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>A True Account of my being taken, and Sufferings during my Captivity.</head>
            <p>UPon the <hi>27th.</hi> day of <hi>Auguſt</hi> 1684. I
<hi>Thomas Phelps</hi> ſet fail from the <hi>Downs</hi> in a Veſſel called the <hi>Succeſs</hi> of <hi>London,</hi> about fourty Tuns, laden with Salt, bound for a place in <hi>Ireland</hi> called the <hi>Ventrey,</hi> where we arrived the <hi>10th.</hi> day of <hi>September:</hi> I ſtayed there ſome while, and kill'd Beaf, deſigning for the <hi>Madera's</hi> and
<hi>Mount Surrat;</hi> accordingly on the <hi>20th.</hi> of <hi>September,</hi> I ſet ſail for the <hi>Madera's,</hi> but my deſign was croſt, and my Voyage ſtopt as followeth: Upon the <hi>5th.</hi> of <hi>October</hi> (being then a Hundred Leagues, <hi>Weſt</hi> off the Rock of <hi>Lisbon)</hi> we ſaw a ſail to windward of us, which immediatly we found to give us chace; we made what ſail we could from him, and night coming on, we had, for about Two hours, loſt ſight of him, but at the riſing of the Moon, he got ſight of us, and quickly came up with us, hail<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing us whence our Ship, we anſwered from <hi>London,</hi> deman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding the like of him, who made anſwer from <hi>Algeir,</hi> and withal commanded us to hoiſt out our Boat, which we re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſed to do, but we brac'd our head-ſailes for him, imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diatly he ſent his Boat towards us, when it was got almoſt by our ſide, we gave them Three ſhouts, which ſo ſurpriz'd them, that they thought it convenient to retire aboard their <pb n="2" facs="tcp:42259:4"/> 
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:42259:4" rendition="simple:additions"/> 
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:42259:5"/> own Ship; We were not a little chear'd at their departure and made from them with all the ſail we could make, for we had not one great Gun, and as for Powder, I believe one ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gle pound was the outmoſt of our ſtore: In the mean time he was hoiſting in of his Boat, I had got above two miles from him, which made me think I was clear of him, and withal that the Ship muſt be an
<hi>Algerine,</hi> ſhe appearing ſo great, that, according to the ſtories in <hi>England,</hi> I thought no ſuch Ship could belong to
<hi>Sallé;</hi> But I found my ſelf within a little while, mightily miſtaken, for as ſoon as his Boat was hoi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted in, he preſently ſetch'd us up again: We had try'd his ſailing all ways, but found we could not wrong him any way; ſo ſeeing him a ſtern, and a thing impoſſible to loſe ſight of us, I put out a light for him, notwithſtanding I was poſſeſt at that time (God knows) with fear enough, but I thought, in the Dark, my ſeeming confidence and reſolution might impoſe upon him, ſo as to fancy I was of ſome force; And truly afterwards he confeſſed to me, that he thought I had ſix Guns aboard and that I did intend to fight him.</p>
            <p>He kept a ſtern of me all night, and in the morning he put out
<hi>Turkiſh</hi> colours, which I anſwered with our <hi>Engliſh;</hi> then he came up, and ſaw I had no boat in ſight, for my boat was ſtow'd down betwixt decks, he commanded me therefore to brace to my head-ſailes, and then he ſent his boat to demand my paſs; Aboard he was an antient
<hi>Moor,</hi> who formerly had been a ſlave in <hi>England</hi> and ſpoke good <hi>Engliſh,</hi> and who was ſet at liberty by our late Gracious King
<hi>Charles</hi> the <hi>2d.</hi> He ſeeing us in readineſs with what arms we had, ask'd me, if I had a mind to break the Peace, he told me I needed not trouble my ſelf to keep them out of our Veſſel, for none of them could be perſwaded to come aboard me.</p>
            <p>I brought him my Cuſtom-houſe-Cocketts, for I had no Paſs: The <hi>Moor</hi> aforeſaid carried them to the Captain, but
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:42259:5" rendition="simple:additions"/> ſoon after returned, and told me that would not ſatisfie the Captain, unleſs the Maſter himſelf would come; I made an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer that I would not come, that I had done what I was o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blig'd to by the Articles 'twixt <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Algiers:</hi> The boat a ſecond time put away for their Ship, and whilſt they were hoiſting in their boat, I made what ſail I could, and was got a mile or more from them again, entertaining better hopes than I was in the night before; But as ſoon as the boat was in and ſtow'd, the <hi>Moors</hi> made ſail and came up with me again, the Captain ordering to tell me, that if I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fus'd to come a board him, he would come aboard me with his Ship; with that he rang'd up my Weather quarter, I im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediatly put a ſtays, which put him into ſome confuſſion, ſo that he was forced to put a ſtays alſo: He had then no Gun, which I could perceive, I ſaw his Ports, and his Waſt was Man-high: As I came about I run under his ſtern, then bore away right before the Wind, he ſoon came up with me, but not one ſhot pas'd all this while, he demanded of me why I clapt a ſtays for to run a thwart his halfe; I anſwered that I doubted he was not of <hi>Algier,</hi> he ſwore in <hi>Engliſh,</hi> to me that he was, elſe before this he would have diſcover'd him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, and withal he told me, that if I did not come aboard, he would ſtraight way ſink me, and ſo he hoiſted out his boat, in the mean time I boar away, but his boat coming up made me bring to again and brace a back; His boat then came a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>board, I ask'd this <hi>Moor,</hi> who ſpoke <hi>Engliſh,</hi> what ſhip of
<hi>Algiers</hi> this was, he very readily without ſtammering told me, ſhe was call'd the <hi>Tagerene</hi> young <hi>Canary</hi> Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mander, I immediatly then went into his boat; ſo ſoon as I came aboard, the Captain ask'd me why I was ſo hard of be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lief, My diſtruſt was ſuch then that I pray'd the Captain now that he had me aboard in his power, to reſolve me whether he were a <hi>Sallé-man</hi> or not, he ſwore to me again that he was of
<hi>Algiers,</hi> and that I ſhould not be wrong'd; He made <pb n="4" facs="tcp:42259:6"/> me ſit down, and caus'd them to ſet Dates and Figgs before me: A little after the Captain told me that he was made acquainted by his men that they ſaw two <hi>Portugueſes</hi> aboard my Ship, and that he would have them out, and then I ſhould be gone about my buſineſs, I told him I had none ſuch aboard, but he would ſee them two men, ſo two men were ſent for, after that he told me there were three more and them he muſt have, well to be ſhort, at laſt he was ſuſpicious that I was a
<hi>Portugueſe</hi> alſo, and to convince me that I was one, I found my entertainment preſently withdrawn? Thus did this faithleſs
<hi>Barbarian</hi> ſerve me, until he had wheadled all my men aboard him except two, and then the valiant <hi>Moors</hi> entred my Veſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſel with abundance of courage, heaving the two remaining <hi>Engliſh</hi> over the head of the Veſſel into the boat.</p>
            <p>Thus were we all Strip'd, the Veſſel Plunder'd in a mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, which they did reſolve to have ſunk, becauſe they were too farr at Sea diſtant from their own coaſt, but Imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diatly we ſaw five ſail bearing down upon us, which ſtartled the <hi>Moors,</hi> putting them into a great fright, obliging them to quit my Veſſel with abundance of Beaf and three Boxes of dry goods aboard, which their fear would not give them leaſure to rummage for: In ſome ſmall time the five Veſſels diſcover'd us, when they came within two Leagues of us, had they bore down afterwards with that reſolution, that they threatned before, the Pirate would never have ſtood to look them in the face, but alaſs like diſtracted fearful game, every of the five Ships took a ſeveral courſe, and being now night they all eſcaped.</p>
            <p>After that we cruiſed about thirty Leagues to the
<hi>Weſt</hi> of the <hi>Northern Cape,</hi> and ſo to the
<hi>Burlings,</hi> but no nearer than Twenty Leagues to the ſhoar, and therefore I imagin there is more ſafety for ſmall veſſels bound that way, to keep the ſhore as near as is poſſible, for I know certainly they never attempt to come near, but endeavour as much as they can,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:42259:6" rendition="simple:additions"/> to avoid the ſhoar becauſe our Men of War uſe to careen at <hi>Lisbon.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I am likewiſe pretty well ſatisfied for that ſmall time that I was amongſt them, (altho' it was too long for my profit) that no
<hi>Sallé-man</hi> will fight a Ship of Ten Guns, which I found true by obſervation of a Country-man from <hi>Briſtol,</hi> whilſt I was aboard: We came up with him and hail'd him, and would have had him put out his Boat, but he refuſed, and withal ſhew'd himſelf ready in his own defence, upon which we were glad to leave him.</p>
            <p>So that to ſatisfie all my Country-men who follow my trade I dare confidently affirm, that if I had a Ship of Ten Guns, and it ſhould be my fortune to encounter any of theſe <hi>Sallé-rouges,</hi> (who all go under the notion of <hi>Algerines,</hi> who are now at peace with
<hi>England)</hi> I would encourage him to ſend his boat, by acquainting him that our Maſter would come aboard and ſhew his paſs, (which is the thing they aim at) And when the boat was come to my ſide, (any man of reaſon may judge then whether ſhe were from <hi>Sallé</hi> or <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giers,</hi> but however I would commit nothing ſhould be judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed a breach of the Peace,
'twixt <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Algiers)</hi> I would heave in a Grapling and ſecure the men, all ſave two, whom I would permitt to return aboard and bring me a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian, or elſe aver my Paſs, if they will not do that, I am then ſatisfied what he is, and think my ſelf obliged to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſend my ſelf from Slavery, but this I am very confident of, that he will never ſtay to diſpute the caſe afterward.</p>
            <p>About a fortnight after I was taken, we met one <hi>Samuel Crampton</hi> who came from <hi>Faro,</hi> and whom we ſoon took without any reſiſtance. The week following we took a ſmall Ketch come from
<hi>Cales,</hi> laden with Sherry and Raiſies and bound for <hi>Limrick, John Elliot</hi> Maſter.</p>
            <p>The number of us Chriſtians taken aboard the Three Prizes was Twenty five, beſides Twelve which were aboard <pb n="6" facs="tcp:42259:7"/> the Pirate, in all Thirty ſeven; We who were newly taken were kept in Irons in the Hold.</p>
            <p>After the taking of theſe Three Veſſels the Pirate made all the ſail he could for <hi>Sallé</hi> to ſave the ſpring Tide, which flows at <hi>Sallé</hi> and <hi>Mamora S S W</hi> about Thirty Leagues: To the <hi>Northward</hi> of <hi>Sallé,</hi> we met a Fleming who came from <hi>Sallé,</hi> and told our Commander that the
<hi>Engliſh-men</hi> of War were at <hi>Tangier</hi> then, attending Captain
<hi>Nicholaſon,</hi> which cauſed us to bear directly for
<hi>Sallé</hi> and fell in directly with the Caſtle, where were no
<hi>Engliſh-men</hi> of War, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the Advice.</p>
            <p>On the Bar of <hi>Sallé</hi> there run a great Sea, which obliged us to come to an Anchor near the <hi>Bar,</hi> where we rid Six hours; then were we poor Chriſtians all let looſe from our Iron<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhackles, wherein we had been confin'd for Twenty days preceeding: the Captain ſent the Boat, as near the Shore to the <hi>South</hi> of the <hi>Bar,</hi> as poſſibly he could, to enquire what News, there they were acquainted that they might ſafely come in the next high Water: whilſt the Boat was gone a Shore, the Moors, we obſerv'd, fell all faſt a ſleep, the Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain alſo, with his Head over the Rail, upon the half-Deck ſeem'd deeply ingag'd: This opportunity me thought was very inviting, I made a propoſal of it to my fellow Slaves, and undertook to do the Captains buſineſs my ſelf: The Chriſtians were forward enough to comply with the motion, and Eleven of the Twelve, (which were Slaves retain'd in the Ship before our being taken) they alſo were willing, if the Twelfth who was Steward in the Ship would have conſented, but this ſneaking varlet prov'd recreant, and for fear of him the other Eleven turn'd alſo Renegadoes to this Heroick and Chriſtian reſolution; I had a mind to have diſpatcht this troubler of our peace out of the way firſt, but the fear that his fellow Slaves would have ſeverely reſented it, reſtrain'd my reſolution; the Slaves Name was
<hi>Will. Robinſon,</hi> he pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed <pb n="7" facs="tcp:42259:7"/> himſelf a Chriſtian in words, but in deed we found more civility from the Moors than him.</p>
            <p>At Four in the Afternoon, we weighed Anchor, and ſtood in for the <hi>Bar,</hi> we ſtruck Twice going over, but without any dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage; it was upon the Firſt day of <hi>November,</hi> after we had helped to moor our Ship, at Night we were all carried aſhore, and conveyed to our Lodging, which was an old Stable, but without Litter or Straw, having nothing ſave the bare dirty Ground for our Bed or Pillow; the next Day we were all carryed aboard the Ship to Unrigg her, and get out her Bal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſt, which we did; about Four in the Afternoon, I was ſent for aſhore to come to the Governour, who paſſed his ſentence on us Three Maſters, that we ſhould go to his Houſe, and there remain, until we were ſent for by the King; we remained at his Houſe Ten days, where our daily employment was to Grind the Corn for the uſe of his Family; at length there came an Order for us, and all the reſt of the Chriſtians to be carryed to the King, whoſe Ordinary and then Reſidence was at <hi>Machaneſs,</hi> a place which this preſent Emperour has ſet his Fancy upon, and beſtows moſt of his care, and employs all Chriſtian Slaves in Building there; it is diſtant from <hi>Sallé</hi> about Seventy Miles, and from <hi>Fez</hi> Thirty.</p>
            <p>In our Journy thither, I cannot forget our Captains extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinary civility, in Accommodating us ſometimes with Bor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ricoes to ride on, ſo that in Two days and a half we arrived thither: The Firſt night we were not brought before our great Maſter, but the following our Captain preſented us before him, and withal ſome <hi>Portugueſe</hi> Plate, which was taken in Mr. <hi>Crampton's</hi> Veſſel; as the Captain gave it into his Hand, the ſurly Tyrant with a ſeeming ſcorn and diſdain heav'd it againſt the Wall, which was the firſt Action I obſerv'd, and did a little diſcover the temper of my new Patron <hi>Muley Iſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mael</hi> Emperour of
<hi>Morocco</hi> and <hi>Fez,</hi> &amp;c. He ordered us to be ſent amongſt the reſt of our fellow Slaves; as we went we <pb n="8" facs="tcp:42259:8"/> were entertain'd with the civilities of the place, and wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comed by the joyfull acclamations and complements of the Moors kicking and ſlapping us all along, which appeared very uncouth to me, who was but a Stranger, but that Night my fellow Captives allayed my wonder, by acquainting me, that what had paſt was nothing, it was only a ſutable Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logue to all the Tragical ſufferings that Chriſtians muſt en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure there whilſt they are Slaves, which were ſo dreadful, that I could willingly, that very Night have ventured my Life to endeavour an eſcape; they Painted out to me the Tyran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nical humour of the Emperour, both towards the Chriſtians and Natives, in ſuch Bloudy Colours,
<hi>viz.</hi> how they had ſeen him Butcher many Thouſands with his own hands, how that none can be ſecure in his preſence for that the varying of a look, a ſmall ſpot in the Garment, or any ſuch inconſiderable circumſtance, will raiſe ſuch a caprice in the Emperours Nod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle, without any other provocation, as to endanger all the Heads before him, and it is very rare if the company eſcape with One or Two only Beheaded, or Lanced through the Body.</p>
            <p>The Second day after my arrival thither, I ſaw him Lance Seven and twenty <hi>Negroes</hi> one after another, and every Day after, until
<hi>New-years-day,</hi> (when he parted to <hi>Santa Cruz</hi> with his Army) I either ſaw or heard of his inhumane, but yet, through cuſtom, to him Natural Barbarities, Killing and Dragging, but this latter is a piece of reſpect obſerved only to Minions and Favourites, Vice-kings and Alcaids; yea his Women are not able by all their Charms to avoid his Fury, but are more the objects of his implacable rage than any other paſſion: I have been ſeveral times in the <hi>Weſt-Indies,</hi> and have ſeen and heard of divers Inhumanities and cruelties pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſed there, I have alſo read in Books, and have heard Lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned men diſcourſe of the <hi>Sicilian</hi> Tyrants and Roman Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perours, but indeed I forget them all, they are not to be
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:42259:8"/> named in compariſon with this Monſter of
<hi>Africk,</hi> a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition of Gore and Duſt, whom nothing can attone but humane Sacrifices, and to be in whoſe court it is much more eligible to be his Horſe or his Mule, than to be his <hi>Privado</hi> or Wife of his boſome, from whoſe greateſt kindneſs my good God ever defend me, for his mercies are cruel: Yea even <hi>Hamed Ben Haddu</hi> who was his Embaſſadour here in <hi>England</hi> Three years ago, altho' he was received and entertain'd here with extraordinary civilities, and carreſs'd every where by all the endearments of kindneſs and reſpect, and altho' by his fineneſs and Mooriſh ſubtilty, he ſtole into the Inclinations of the well-meaning and good natur'd <hi>Engliſh,</hi> ſo that he obtain'd the reputation of Ingenuity and candour, Yet the Dog has return'd to his Vomit, and by woful experiment, all my Country-men, who come under his power, find him a harſh and cruel Maſter, who manag'd his affairs here with deep diſſimulation, and now improves his knowledge of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh</hi> affairs, to the detriment and ruin of all the Kings Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects, with whom he has to do; if it be his fortune to meet or paſs by any of them, his cuſtom is (as all the <hi>Engliſh</hi> can atteſt) to ſalute them with a deviliſh Curſe to the beſt of my remembrance expreſt thus, <hi>Alli Haztebuck,</hi> i. e. <hi>God roaſt your Father:</hi> he is indeed reckoned a great Maſter in the art of Diſſimulation and Flattery, a qualification, which ſeems very requiſite in a Courtier of ſuch a Barbarous Bloody Tyrant as his Maſter is.</p>
            <p>But to proceed, my fellow Chriſtians in the next place, ſhewed me the ſtaff of their life there, <hi>i. e.</hi> their Bread, which was of Barley, but black, and withal it ſtunk, the Corn being kept Seven years under Ground before us'd, one Days allowance if ſold, would yield only Nine Fluces, which a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mount to Three Farthings; Fleſh is cheap, both Mutton and Beef, but Mony is ſcarce, Two pounds and a half of Beef, are ordinarily ſold for a Blankil, <hi>i. e.</hi> Two pence half-peny, <pb n="10" facs="tcp:42259:9"/> and Two pounds of Mutton at the ſame rate; good white-Bread is alſo plentiful, half as cheap as in <hi>England;</hi> but what is this to the Slaves who have-not a Farthing, and not a bit is allow'd us without Mony; I am confident there is many a Chriſtian there, who hath not taſted a morſel of Fleſh in Five Months time.</p>
            <p>The Country is a pleaſant Champion Country, very Fruit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, well Watered, productive of all ſorts of Fruit in plenty; we Chriſtians who arrived laſt, were excuſed for Two days from Labour, only we were inſtructed in our deportments to our <hi>Negro-</hi>Taskmaſters, who afterwards gave us ſevere cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtiſment for our miſtakes and lapſes: our Work and Daily Labour was continually Building of Houſes and Walls; the Materials and Method is very Forreign and will appear ſtrange to my Country-men here; there are Boxes of Wood of dimenſions according to pleaſure, theſe we fill with Earth powdred and Lime, and Gravel well beat together and tempered with Water, and when full, we remove the Box according to order, and withdraw the Box Planks, and leave this matter to dry, which then will acquire an incredible hardneſs, and is very laſting, for we have ſeen Walls of ſome Hundred years ſtanding as we were informed, and all that time has not been able to do them any prejudice.</p>
            <p>The King himſelf (what the reaſon of his humour may be I never had the curioſity to ask him) will ſometimes vouch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſafe to work in the Lime and Durt for an hour together, and will bolt out an encouraging word to the Slaves them, <hi>viz.</hi> as I remember, <hi>Liferus,</hi> that is,
<hi>God ſend you to your own Countries,</hi> but I judge, he either does not ſpeak from his Heart, or elſe he hopes God will not anſwer the Prayers of ſuch a wicked wretch; with this ſort of Labour I made a ſhift to paſs away all the Winter, and indeed without a quible, I had no other ſhift or ſhirt, only the Charity of my fellow Slaves, who were better provided, accommoda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted <pb n="11" facs="tcp:42259:9"/> me with a covering from the Cold, which elſe would have endangered my life.</p>
            <p>The Reader, I ſuppoſe, will not think it ſtrange, if I was diſſatisfied and very weary of my condition, and therefore I did often rummage all my thoughts, for ſome expedient to eaſe me of this accurſed way, not of Living, but Starving and Dying daily: My mind did often flatter me with the greateſt poſſibility of Liberty by running away, and ſo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fident I was, that I diſcovered my intentions to ſeveral Chriſtians, eſpecially to thoſe of my near acquaintance, who by no means could be induc'd to hear the difficulties and dangers that attended ſuch a reſolution: In the mean time my Friends in <hi>England</hi> had taken ſome care for my Ran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome, and had given order to Mr <hi>Luddington,</hi> an
<hi>Engliſh</hi> Merchant in <hi>Barbary,</hi> to endeavour my relief if One hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred and fifty Pounds would effect it, which Sum Mr. <hi>Lud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dington</hi> acquainted me, he was ready to disburſe, if I could cut, (that is, agree with my Patron for my Ranſome) for Six hundred or Seven hundred pieces of Eight: I profered the ſaid Sum, but it would not be accepted; upon which I lookt upon my condition as deſperate, my forlorn and languiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſtate of life without any hopes of Redemption, (which on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly could ſupport our Spirts in the midſt of ſuch great affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions, and Bondage to thoſe upon whom God and Nature ſeems to have impreſt characters of Slavery to the reſt of Mankind) appeared far worſe than the terrours of a moſt cruel Death, I ſet up then my fixt and unalterable reſolution to eſcape whatever fate attended it, leaving the event to providence; I had more than conjecture, that preſent Death was to be the reward of my endeavours if I were retaken, for Three <hi>Spaniards,</hi> who ſome Two Months before were taken, making their eſcape, the King cauſed them to be brought be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore him, and with his own hands prov'd their Butcher, and Executioner, which cruel proceedings did wholly diſhearten <pb n="12" facs="tcp:42259:10"/> the poor Spirited Chriſtians, and baniſhed all ſuch reſoluti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons quite out of their minds: At length I opened my mind to Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi> (who about a Year and a half before, had made an unlucky attempt to run away, but being brought back he had the Baſtinado in ſuch a ſort that he could not work for a Twelve Month, having Irons continually upon his Leggs) but notwithſtanding, ſuch was his love of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Liberty, that he freely told me, that he would adven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture with any fair opportunity; after I had him thus engag'd by his promiſe, I gave him no reſt, until we had pitch'd upon a Day; we alſo took into our Cabal and ſhare of our For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunes, Two <hi>Briſtol-men,</hi> who were ready at an hours war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, when we appointed.</p>
            <p>There are at <hi>Machaneſs</hi> at preſent about Eight hundred Chriſtians of all Nations, Two hundred and ſixty whereof are
<hi>Engliſh,</hi> ſeveral of which have tendred Mony for their Ranſom, ſome Seven hundred, ſome Five hundred pieces of Eight, ſome more, ſome leſs, but the King ſtill put them off with this, that he would clear none particularly, but that they ſhould go all together.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>January</hi> the Firſt, The King ſet forward towards
<hi>Santa Cruz,</hi> with an Army of about Sixty thouſand men, deſigning to quel his Nephew, who had made a formidable Inſurrection againſt him, in that part of his Dominions: We Chriſtians could not Inform our ſelves of the certain proceedings of theſe Armies, neither did we much care, fight Dog, fight Bear, but this we learnt, that it will be Two or Three years before his return, and it is not to be ſuppos'd that any particular Chriſtian will be releas'd until he return; beſides, there is no hopes to be laid upon the moſt ſolemn word and proteſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of this ſwarthy Infidel <hi>Muley Iſmael,</hi> for, as I have been inform'd, about Four or Five years ago, by an agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment with Collonel <hi>Kirk,</hi> all the <hi>Engliſh</hi> ſlaves were to be ſet at liberty at the rate of Two hundred pieces of Eight a
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:42259:10"/> head, and the bargain was ſo far ſtruck, that the Chriſtians were got a Mile out of Town, But the accurſed Jews, (the ſtench and peſt of the Nations of the Earth, Malicious to all Man-kind and loathſome and abominable whereever they come, who not only have the blood of the Saviour of the World lying upon their heads, but are accountable for the blood of many Thouſands of his Members which they daily ſhed) Theſe wicked Enemies of Chriſtianity, brought back theſe poor Chriſtians into the houſe of bondage thus, they proſſered the Emperour as much mony as the King of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> tendred for the Chriſtians Ranſome, if ſo be he would only lend them for a while, to build a City for the Jews, and then they ſhould be reſtor'd to the King; The covetous Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant ſoon clos'd with theſe advantageous terms, and the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans were turn'd over to the Jews, who imploy'd them Three years in building a City, but when finiſh'd, ſee the juſt Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of God! The Jews were turn'd out, and forc'd to give place to the Moors: Another remarkable ſtory concerning the Jews I cannot but inſert upon this occaſion: About Three years ago, Mr. <hi>Bowrey</hi> of
<hi>Briſtol</hi> was, with Twenty ſail more, taken by the
<hi>Sallé-men, Bowrey</hi> had a parcel of Soap in his Ship, which then did belong to the King; <hi>Ben Haddu</hi> Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſſadour in <hi>England</hi> deſir'd to buy this Soap of the King, but a Jew out bid him, and ſo had the Soap, for which dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling the Ambaſſador kept a grudge in his mind againſt the Jews, and was reveng'd on them, after this manner, whilſt I was there. He inform'd the King that the Jews had im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pos'd upon him and couzen'd him of Fifty thouſand pieces of Eight in the matter of the Soap, upon which the King clapt up Ten of the chief Jews in Priſon, until they ſhould either pay the ſaid Sum, or elſe reſtore the Soap, which it is to be ſuppoſed, hath been fold in Chriſtendom Two years ago.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="escape" type="account">
            <pb n="14" facs="tcp:42259:11"/>
            <head>
               <hi>An Account of my Eſcape, Mr.</hi> Edmund Baxter, <hi>and others from</hi> Barbary.</head>
            <p>AFter a ſerious conſideration, finding that no proffers for my redemption would be accepted, I committed the conduct of my proceedings to Almighty providence reſolving to make an Eſcape in company of Three more,
<hi>Edmund Baxter, Anthony Bayle,</hi> and <hi>James Ingram.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>On the <hi>29th.</hi> of <hi>May,</hi> agreeing with our Guardian-Moors for a <hi>Blankil, (i. e.) 2d. ob.</hi> a piece, we had the liberty to be excus'd from work that day, we went there fore to the Town of
<hi>Machaneſs,</hi> and having but a ſmall ſtock of caſh about us,
<hi>viz.</hi> nine <hi>Blankils,</hi> we laid it out in Bread, and two ſmall Bullocks bladders, with a little Burdock to carry Water in.</p>
            <p>About Three of the clock in the Afternoon we began our journey deſigning to go as far as an Old houſe, call'd the Kings houſe, diſtant about Three miles from <hi>Machaneſs,</hi> reſolving to conceal our ſelves about that houſe until night, and promiſing to our ſelves the greater ſecurity, becauſe we knew ſome Chriſtians uſed commonly to work there, but proceeding in our journey, we diſcover'd upon a loaded Horſe the Moor who lived at that houſe, which oblig'd us to quicken our pace, and keep a head of him, for, if he ſhould come up with us, he would eaſily diſcover that we <pb n="15" facs="tcp:42259:11"/> did not belong to the ſaid houſe, We made haſt therefore before him, and coming near the houſe we diſcover'd about Twenty Moors ſitting there; which accident of being hem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in behind and before by theſe our enemies, put us into a great fright, and had in all likely hood ſpoil'd our deſign, in the very entrance, if providence had not preſented to our view, on one ſide of the houſe, a parcel of Lime-kills, to which, without the Moors obſervation we immediatly ſtruck up, where we abſconded our ſelves by lying flat upon our bellies; about half an hour after came two Mooriſh women thither, to gather up ſome looſe wood, we conſidering it very inconvenient to ſhew our ſelves fearful, leſt we ſhould be taken for Renagadoes, ſpoke to them, but they return'd us no anſwer, following their buſineſs, and taking us, as vve judged, either for Moors or Chriſtians employ'd about the ſaid Lime-kills ſo vve continued there vvithout any further moleſtation, until night, vvhen vve proceeded on our jour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney, traveling about Eighteen miles that night, vve paſſed by a great many Tents, vvhence the Dogs came out and barkt at us, and the Moors alſo favv us, but ſaid nothing, miſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king us for their Country-men.</p>
            <p>That night vve croſt the great River, vvhich runs dovvn to
<hi>Mamora,</hi> about Eighteen miles diſtance from <hi>Machaneſs,</hi> and about a mile from the bank of the River, vve found a convenient buſh, vvhere vve took up our lodging all the day follovving, vvithout any diſturbance: At night vve found our ſelves oblig'd to return to the ſaid River, to furniſh us vvith Water, the littleneſs of our veſſel, vvhich contain'd not above a Gallon, being a great hindrance in our journey: We continued our progreſs Tvvelve miles that night, vvhich prov'd very tireſome by reaſon of the vveeds and buſhes, and the nights vvere not ſo long as vve vviſh'd; juſt about Day-break, vve found a convenient buſh near to a great Valley, vvhere vve repos'd our ſelves; as ſoon as the day
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:42259:12"/> broke clear, we ſaw abundance of Cattle graſing in the bottom, with Moors, who lookt after them, but, by Gods pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence, none came near us, ſo that we lay ſafe all that day, being the laſt day of
<hi>May.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>At night we ſet forwards, keeping the Woods, where were no Mooriſh Inhabitants, only wild beaſts, the leſs ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vage and formidable, which we often ſaw, but they never attempted to come near us, we travel'd about Ten miles that night, and then croſſed a River, which ſupplied us with Water, whereof we were in want; on the other ſide of the River, we obſerv'd the footſteps of a great many Cattle, which rendred the place, as we thought, unſafe for us, we made therefore a little further progreſs in the morning, to the top of the Hill, where under a large Oak we found a buſh convenient for our reception that day, but within a little while we were diſturb in our repoſe, obſerving the Cattle to come graſing up the Hill, directly to that buſh, with Moors at their heels, with all haſt therefore we pact up our luggage and ran a mile further, without being diſcover'd, until we came to a Pear tree, furniſh'd with long-graſs a round him, there we took up our quarters all that day, being the Firſt of
<hi>June.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The night following, we intended to proceed, but it plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed God, to ſtrike me lame with the Gout, ſo that I was not able to ſtand, I was forced therefore to remain there all that night, and the day enſuing, which was a great hindrance to my companions, and affliction to my ſelf: The readieſt expedient to remedy my diſtemper, which I could think upon was this, we made a fire in a hole in the ground, and I put my Foot into the hole to draw away the pain, having alſo a Lancet with us, I endeavour'd to breath a Vein in my Foot, but I could not effect it, for the Lancet would not enter, however, I found ſome eaſe by the force of the fire: My company being ſenſible of the delay, which my diſtemper <pb n="17" facs="tcp:42259:12"/> occaſion'd, began to be mov'd, inſomuch that they told me, that if I could not march with them that night, they muſt hold themſelves oblig'd to take leave of me, which added a great affliction to my ſorrow, inſomuch as I was the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor and firſt mover of this eſcape; That I might not there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore be forſaken by my companions, and in compliance to their importunity, I reſolved to ſtrain my outmoſt power.</p>
            <p>The third of <hi>June</hi> at night I endeavoured to go, but in great pain, ſo that we could not proceed above Three miles, when I was forc'd to pray my Companions to ſtay but that night, and I did not queſtion, but by Gods bleſſing, to be able to travel with them the next, they conſented, and ſo we took up our lodging for the remainder of that night, under another Pear-tree.</p>
            <p>The fourth of <hi>June</hi> I kept baking my foot all the day in the Ground, till about two in the Afternoon, in the mean while, I procur'd Mr.
<hi>Baxter</hi> to make me a wooden Leg, which accordingly he did, I perſwaded them, then, to tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vel about Three or Four miles that afternoon, which would a little eaſe the labour of the night, they agreed, I travel'd about Four miles with that Leg, and then reſted till night on the top of a high Hill, whence we ſaw a great plain valley before us.</p>
            <p>At night we ſhap'd our courſe clear of the Tents, and tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vel'd over the edge of the plain, about Six miles; We paſt by ſeveral fields of corn, the Moors in the mean time hallow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to frighten the wild beaſts from them: Croſſing of a Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver that night, we ſaw and heard ſeveral Lyons, ſome ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach'd ſo near that we could almoſt have touch'd them, but as ſoon as we ſtrook fire, which we had prepar'd for that very purpoſe, they preſently vaniſh'd; when the light began to diſplay it ſelf, we took our quarters for the next day, which was <hi>June</hi> the Fifth; At night we continued our courſe, when I was ſtill lame, which was a great hindrance to my <pb n="18" facs="tcp:42259:13"/> company, but we were loath to part, our bread alſo was al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt at an end, the conſideration whereof oblig'd me to ſtrain hard to get Eight miles that night: By reſting the next day I found my ſelf to be ſomething better, but then to qualifie my joy for this, Another companion <hi>Anthony Bayle</hi> began to ſink and give over.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>June</hi> the Sixth, We ſet onward, and meaſur'd Ten miles that night, when we came to a great Swamp, there my pain renewing, I fain would have perſwaded them to ſtay but by no intreaties could perſwade them, ſo reſolving to part, we ſhar'd our Bread, which came to two half Rusks a peice; I endeavour'd to allure my weak wearied Brother to abide with me, comforting him with the expectation of Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dens, where we two more eaſily than the company of Four, might provide for our ſelves; He would not ſtay; Being preſt thus with the conſideration of being leſt alone, I Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolv'd to put forward, when it pleaſed God, that my foot became perfectly whole and clear of the Gout; That night we travel'd over a high barren Hill, where we fancied we heard the Suſs and noiſe of the Sea, which encourag'd us to mend our pace until we met with a Garden, where we ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther'd about a dozen of ſmall Pumpkins, a very comforta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble aſſiſtance to us, now that our Bread was all ſpent, for ſome we eat raw, and ſome we roaſted in the ground, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by we found our ſelves conſiderably refreſht: That night we made no more then Eight miles, for meeting with a great Oak which was blown down, we thought it inconvenient to overſlip ſuch an advantageous retirement for the next day, which we were the more deſirous off, becauſe we heard a great many <hi>Moors,</hi> tho' we could not ſee them.</p>
            <p>All the next day we lay ſtill and with exceeding content<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment we heard the noiſe of the Sea, at night we put on and came to the ſhoar, where we found whereabout we then were, <hi>viz.</hi> to the <hi>Southward</hi> of
<hi>Mamora,</hi> we directed our <pb n="19" facs="tcp:42259:13"/> Courſe then
<hi>Northward</hi> for Two miles, when we could di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcern the Caſtle, but knowing that we could not go to the <hi>Northward</hi> of the Caſtle, becauſe the great River goes di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rectly up into the Country, we turn'd back about a mile, and finding a convenient buſh, we reſted there all the next day, hearing and ſeeing a great many Cattle, but none came near us.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>June</hi> the Eighth, We gathered about half a Peck of Snailes, and caught a Land-Tortois, which we roaſted and eat har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tily, that day alſo, we ſaw a Ship in the Offing, when night was come, we made down towards the Caſtle, and before we were aware we fell upon a Moor making a fire, which forc'd us to draw back, the Moor not diſcerning us, we fetcht then a compaſs, and by another way came down to the Caſtle, there we found a ſtrong watch, which did wholly diſcourage our expectations of relief from that place, ſo we ſet up our Reſolutions for <hi>Sallé,</hi> about Eighteen or Twenty miles to the <hi>Southward,</hi> to ſee what good could be done there, But before we parted with <hi>Mamora,</hi> we made bold with a little Barley and Guinny corn, growing under the Caſtle, of each whereof we gathered about a quarter of a Peck, to ſerve our neceſſities, and then we betook our ſelves to our former nights refuge, the Buſh, and after having conſulted how to ſteer our courſe for <hi>Sallé,</hi> the reſult whereof was a long the Sea-ſide, we reſted all the next day without diſtur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bance.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>June</hi> the Ninth, We travel'd along the Sea-ſide, where we ſaw a great deal of Raſt-timber, we concluded therefore, ſeeing the Ship in the Offing, to make a Raft, which accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dingly we did, and put off with it, but it would not ſwim, boyart with us all, we came therefore a ſhore, and cut all our Laſhings, leaving it to the mercy of the Sea: We tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vel'd Five miles towards <hi>Sallé</hi> that night, fearing leaſt by ſtaying long thereabout we ſhould be diſcovered, for our foot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:42259:14"/> and trayling of the Timber had made ſuch an Impreſſion in the ſand as if an Hundred men had been there; That night we took up our quarters in a Fig-tree, about Seven miles ſhort of
<hi>Sallé</hi> where was no Inhabitant.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>June</hi> the Tenth at night, we made forward to
<hi>Sallé,</hi> in the Road, we ſell upon a parcel of Tents, where though the Dogs were ready to ſeize us, and the Moors themſelves call'd to us, We made no anſwer and travel'd on, without any far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther trouble or danger, until we came to <hi>Sallé,</hi> as ſoon as we came thither, we made towards the Gardens, and gathered ſome Pumkins, and becauſe night was far ſpent, we retrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted about a mile out of Town, to find ſome place which might ſecure us from diſcovery; we pitch'd upon a Buſh in a great Valley, wherein we reſolv'd to encloſe our ſelves the day following: About Eleven of the clock of that day, we eſpied a Boy with a Dog keeping of Sheep, but yet not forgeting his game, which was hunting of Partridges; He beat the buſh wherein we were lodg'd, and threvv in Stones, and the Dog alſo did his part, barking and courſing about the buſh, buthy miracle as we thought, we were not eſpied, tho' we diſcover'd abundance of fear amongſt our ſelves, for if we had been taken notice of, we could not otherwiſe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſult our own ſafety, than by the death of that poor ſilly Lad.</p>
            <p>The eleventh day being paſt, at night we made a deſcent to the River of <hi>Sallé,</hi> about a mile above the Town, where we found a Boat, but could not with all our ſtrength launch her: <hi>Anthony Bayle</hi> and I who were the only ſwimmers in our company, made over to the
<hi>South-ſide</hi> of the River, to ſee what purchaſe we could make there, we found indeed Three boats, but they were all aground, ſo that we could do no good with them; But in ſearching about the new Ships, (which Five in number are building there) we found two Oares, with which we ſwam over to our conſorts, and <pb n="21" facs="tcp:42259:14"/> all together we went down by the Rivers ſide, to the Har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours mouth, but we could meet with no boat to put our Oares in; We ſaw two <hi>Dutch-</hi>men in the River, but they kept a diligent watch, which hindred us from carrying away their boat; We concluded therefore to bury our Oares in the ſand at ſome remarkable place, and ſo we betook our ſelves to find out a ſanctuary for the day following; We found a Fig-tree full of leaves, in an unfrequented place, as we thought, on the <hi>North-ſide</hi> of the River, yet within call of the Ships, vvhich then vvere a building? Under the Covert of this little Tree, tho' ſurrounded vvith Enemies and dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers, vve reſolv'd to expect the protection of the next day; The Reader may poſſibly judge this an inſtance of a Roman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tick courage, and an effect rather of raſh boldneſs than pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent conſideration; Truly, he is in the right, for vve our ſelves vvere of the ſame mind, about the middle of the next day, upon this occaſion, a Moor vvho had nevvly vvaſht his cloaths, directs his courſe directly to our Tree, and there hangs up his <hi>Al hage</hi> to dry vvhilſt he himſelf ſat dovvn not far off, to lovvſe himſelf, an't pleaſe you; if providence did hinder him from diſcerning us, I aſſure you it vvas not for vvant of provocation, as vve all confeſt, and indeed I never in my life vvas in ſuch a trembling fit, as that lovvſie Raſcal put me into.</p>
            <p>The Tvvelfth day of <hi>June</hi> being paſt, at night vve came dovvn again to the River, to look after a boat, vvhich vve had obſerv'd vvas moor'd in the River, half a mile higher than vvhere vve found the Oares, this, vve vvho could ſvvim found and brought to our conſorts, We padl'd her dovvn the River cloſe by the <hi>Dutch</hi> men, vvho ſavv us, but ſaid nothing, then vve put a ſhore, and fetcht our Oares, vve continued padling, until vve had paſt a <hi>French-</hi>man, lying at the Bars mouth, vvho plainly ſavv us, but ſaid nothing; So ſoon as vve had left him behind us, vve ſhipp'd out our Oares, and <pb n="22" facs="tcp:42259:15"/> Rovving right into the Sea, our courſe by the <hi>North-ſtar</hi> vvas
<hi>Weſt-North-Weſt:</hi> vvhen vve had Rovved Four Miles or thereabout, vve diſcern'd a Ship at Anchor, vvhich ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lig'd us to alter our courſe, and Rovv <hi>Northward,</hi> until vve had paſt her, fearing leaſt ſhe might be a <hi>Sallè-</hi>Ship, and vve had learn'd at <hi>Machaneſs</hi> that Tvvo of them vvere a cruizing at that time, and not yet come in, therefore it vvas, that in diſtruſt of this Ship, vve altered our courſe; vve Rovved about Tvvo Leagues vvithout the Ship, and lay upon our Oares; vvhen Day broke up clear, vve ſavv the Ship vvith her Sailes looſe, I then acquainted my Conſorts, that in my judgment, if the Ship vvere of <hi>Sallé</hi> ſhe vvould make in for the <hi>Bar</hi> at that time, becauſe the Tide and the Sea breeze vvere then both favourable, it being High-vvater at Seven of the Clock, but if ſhe vvere an <hi>Engliſh</hi> Man of War, as vve inceſſantly vviſh'd, then vve thought the Sea-breeze vvould make her ſtand off to Sea: Notwithſtanding our opinions were various, and we were doubtful what to do; at length I perſwaded my conſorts, with much ado, to row in and make her hull, then the Ship ſtood off, and at length ſaw us, we pull'd aboard, and found her to be the <hi>Lark-Friggot</hi> Captain
<hi>Leighton</hi> Commander; after ſome Examination and Diſcourſe about the Methods and Means of our Eſcape, I propounded to the Captain a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign which had newly taken ſtrong poſſeſſion of my Fancy, it was this, that if he would accommodate me with his Boat, and thoſe belonging to the other Two Men of War, which were in Company, I would undertake to Pilot them in, and to burn what Ships were then at <hi>Mamora;</hi> The Captain im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately ſtood to the <hi>Northward,</hi> and came up with the other Two Ships, which were the <hi>Bonaventure</hi> and the <hi>Gray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hound;</hi> The Admiral was then Sick at <hi>Cales,</hi> ſo Captain <hi>Macdonald</hi> being Eldeſt Captain, we went aboard him, and ſending for Mr. <hi>Fairborne,</hi> who was then Captain under <pb n="23" facs="tcp:42259:15"/> Captain <hi>Prieſtman,</hi> who was Sick as aboveſaid, they held a Council about thoſe propoſitions which I had made, at firſt they ſeemed unpracticable, by reaſon of many difficulties, but eſpecially of the <hi>Bar,</hi> which is worſe than that of <hi>Sallé;</hi> But then when upon Second thoughts they conſidered the forwardneſs of Men, who but that very Day had eſcapt a heavy Slavery, and yet were willing that very Night to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gage in the action, they concluded it both poſſible and fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible, ſo they entertain'd with approbation what I had pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pos'd; After which I immediately return'd with Captain
<hi>Leighton</hi> aboard the <hi>Lark,</hi> and communicated the reſult of the Council with my Comrade Mr. <hi>Baxter,</hi> who was heartily pleas'd with what was undertaken, and willing to go along, ſo he was ordered to go in the
<hi>Bonaventure's</hi> Boat, and was very ſerviceable, and who was better acquianted with that Bar, than I was. Immediately orders were given to ſhave ſome Deal-boards, and ſaw ſome Tarr-barrels, and make rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy with all expedition; by Seven at Night, all things were in readineſs, the Friggots were riding Two Leagues from Shore, orders were given that the Boat in which I was, viz. the <hi>Gray-hound's,</hi> ſhould go a head, Commanded by Captain
<hi>Macdonald,</hi> who behaved himſelf indeed with great Courage and Reſolution, and the reſt had orders to follow us; there were Three Barges in all, and one Yawl, the number of Men concern'd in the action, was Forty two, who all had ſtrict charge upon pain of Death, not to ſeek after Plunder, which was punctually obſerv'd. About Eight at Night we put off from the Ships, and betwixt Nine and Ten, we fell a little to the <hi>Northward</hi> of the <hi>Bar,</hi> but by Mr. <hi>Baxter's</hi> aſſiſtance, we quickly righted our ſelves, and found the <hi>Bar;</hi> there was a great noiſe upon the Shore, all thereabout had taken the Alarm, which did nothing diſcourage us, we proceeded luſtily, without any concernment at their hideous outcries, which when the Moors perceiv'd, and that we advanc'd with
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:42259:16"/> undaunted Reſolutions, they thought it beſt to flie betimes and ſecure themſelves and their Caſtle; in the mean time we purſu'd our deſign towards the Ships, aboard which, there being a great many Lights, we obſerv'd the Moors looking over the ſides of the firſt we came to, which was the bigger of the Two, they call'd to us, to keep off, we anſwered them with about Twenty Granado-ſhells, which ſoon drove them overboard; they had not far indeed to eſcape, for the Caſtle Wall was within a Boats length of the Ship, ſo with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any difficulty we preſently entred; one Moor we found aboard, who was preſently cut in pieces, another was ſhot in the head, endeavouring to eſcape upon the Cable, we were not long in taking in our Shavings and Tarr-barrels, and ſo ſet her on fire in ſeveral places, ſhe being very apt to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive what we deſign'd, for there were ſeveral Barrels of Tar upon the Deck, and ſhe was newly Tarr'd as if on pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe; whilſt we were ſetting her on fire, we heard a noiſe of ſome people in the Hold, we opened the Skuttles, and thereby ſav'd the lives of Four Chriſtians, Three <hi>Dutch-men</hi> and One <hi>French,</hi> who told us that the Ship on fire was Admiral and belong'd to
<hi>Aly-Hackum,</hi> and the other which we ſoon after ſerv'd with the ſame ſauce, had the Name of <hi>Plummage Cortibe,</hi> which was the very Ship, which in <hi>October</hi> laſt took me Captive, I cannot deny that I was poſſeſſed with an extraordinary ſatisfaction to ſee this Ship on fire, and I could not but admire the wonderful providence of God, to whom alone Vengeance belongeth, in vindicating my cauſe, and making me an unwitting inſtrument of revenge, for the injuries I received from the owners of this Veſſel.</p>
            <p>Such was the fierceneſs of the Flames, that vve vvere forc'd to keep off from the Ships ſides, vvhereby vve be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came obnoxious to the ſhot of the Moors, vvho from the Walls of the Caſtle made a great firing upon us, both of ſmall and great Guns, but vvith little or no Execution, for
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:42259:16"/> our Men, by the light of the great fire having them in per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect view upon the Walls, made ſmart returns upon them, firing inceſſantly upon them, and with that eagerneſs, that they quite neglected their Oares, ſo that if the Tide had not turn'd to Ebb, we ſhould have run a great riſque, our Men were ſo full of joy, hooping and hallowing at the ſight of ſo deſirable a Bon-fire, that they never minded the dangers they might be ſubject to; we were therefore forced to row the
<hi>Bonaventure's</hi> Yawl, who had loſt all her Oares. In all this Action we had but one Man mortally wounded, and two or three more ſlightly hurt: after we had compleated our buſineſs, and abſolutely deſtroyed theſe Ships, we return'd out of the River, over the <hi>Bar,</hi> and pull'd aboard the Friggots, Captain <hi>Macdonald</hi> received us kindly, and gratified us with the entertainment of his Ship very frankly, aboard which we ſtaid until we came to <hi>Cales,</hi> there we went aſhore, deſigning a paſſage for <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> with the firſt opportunity; Captain <hi>Macdonald</hi> gave us Certificates of our ſervice in the late Action, and then Mr.
<hi>Baxter</hi> and I took leave of him; we did not ſtay long at
<hi>Cales,</hi> before we met with an opportunity for <hi>England</hi> aboard Captain <hi>Atkins,</hi> who came from <hi>Leghorn</hi> and was bound for
<hi>London,</hi> who very willingly granted us paſſage with him, and gave us civil and welcome entertainment, whom God reward and all other our Benefactors, parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cularly (tho' to ſome Readers it may ſeems immaterial, yet when occaſion offers, not to remember, to all good Men will appear unthankful, and I had rather be tax'd with im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertmence than ungratitude) Mr.
<hi>Hodges,</hi> who beſtow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed upon us Four pieces of Eight in our neceſſity, God return his Charity into his own Boſome with bleſſing and encreaſe, and honeſt Captain <hi>Gutteridge,</hi> who ſent a Barrel of Beaf and a Hundred weight of Bread, leaſt we ſhould lie too chargeable upon Captain <hi>Atkins</hi> in our <pb n="26" facs="tcp:42259:17"/> paſſage home, who the Firſt day of <hi>July</hi> 1685. ſet Sail from <hi>Cadiz,</hi> and arrived in the <hi>Downs</hi> the <hi>26th.</hi> of that Month.</p>
            <p>Thus have I given a ſhort and plain account of my Captivity and Eſcape, with the circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances that attended it, and tho' poſſibly my Stile may appear rough and unpoliſh'd, which the courteous Reader I hope will a little ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe, expecting no other from a blunt Seaman, acquainted with nothing ſo much as Dangers and Storms, yet I do profeſs I have Penn'd this Narrative with all the ſincerity and truth, that becomes a plain-dealing
<hi>Engliſh-man:</hi> My de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign and aim in all (kind Country-man and courteous Reader) is, to excite with me thy praiſes to our God the only deliverer, who hath de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered me from a cruel and ſevere Captivity, and withal to ſtir up thy grateful reſentments, for the happineſs, peace and freedom, that thou enjoyeſt under ſo excellent and well tempered a Government, but moſt eſpecially to move thy pitty for the afflictions of
<hi>Joſeph,</hi> to excite thy compaſſionate regard to thoſe poor Country-men now Languiſhing in mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſery and Irons, to endeavour their releaſment according to thy power, at leaſt by impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuning
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:42259:17"/> Heaven, that during their Captivity God would ſupport them with his Grace, to bear patiently their afflictions, and to reſiſt all Temptations until in his good appointed time, he vouchſafe them a happy deliverance, <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
